Narrator: 3
Life in prison
Speaker: Modern prisons often hold thousands of inmates,
and prison design now aims to limit the movement of prisoners around the facility.
Instead of large blocks of cells,
smaller modules are arranged around an outdoor exercise yard
and each module may be supervised by only one prison officer.
Some prisoners may be placed in a cell on their own
in solitary confinement for their own safety, for example, celebrities,
former police officers, and those convicted of certain types of crimes, e.g. against children.
Maximum security prisons are for inmates considered dangerous,
disruptive, or likely to try to escape.
They can be locked up often for up to 23 hours a day and are under constant surveillance.
At the other end of the spectrum are open prisons,
which allow free movement to work or do activities;
some prisoners may be allowed home leave or part-time employment outside the prison.
The modern prison system intends a prison sentence to be less of a punishment
and more about rehabilitation,
so that the prisoner can return to normal life and not reoffend.
Prisons provide healthcare and education,
but also things like gyms and weightlifting rooms, sports teams,
arts and crafts, and television sets.
Such services are controversial: some people claim that prisons are ‘soft’ on inmates,
while others argue that it is dehumanizing not to provide recreation.
Prison administrators say that keeping prisoners occupied helps to maintain order
and that prisoners can be deprived of recreation as punishment.